I'm back in the burger project and here, I now want to add some testing. For that
Ben burger projesine geri dndm ve imdi, biraz test yapmak istiyorum. Bunun iin nce npm balangcnn
we should first make sure that npm start is not running because we need to install some additional packages
almadndan emin olmalyz, nk sadece aka deil ayn zamanda enzim kullandmzdan
after all we're not just using jest but also enzyme.
sonra baz ek paketler kurmamz gerekiyor.
Now if we have a look at our package.json file and we scroll a little bit up, we see that jest
imdi paketimize bir gz atabilirsek. json dosyas ve biraz ilerledike, jestin gerekten
is indeed installed, you might have a different version but it should be installed
kurulu olduunu gryoruz, farkl bir versiyona sahip olabilirsiniz ama kurulmal
but enzyme isn't.
ama enzim yok.
So let's first of all install that with npm install --save enzyme,
yleyse, npm install --save enzimiyle ilk nce unu yapalm, imdi
now that alone won't do the trick though,
tek bamza hile yapmyoruz,
we need to install two additional packages to make it work correctly with jest and react.
aka ve tepkiyle doru almas iin iki ek paket daha kurmamz gerekiyor.
The first is that we need to install the react test renderer package,
Bunlardan birincisi, reaksiyon testi oluturucu paketini kurmamz gerektiidir. Bu,
that is a dependency of enzyme which we need to install separately and we need to install an adapter
ayr olarak kurmamz gereken enzimin bamlldr ve u
of the enzyme package to our current react
andaki reaksiyon versiyonuna
version. So here this is the enzyme adapter-react-16 version 4 react 16.
enzim paketinin bir adaptrn takmamz gerekir. Yani burada bu enzim adaptr-tepki-16 versiyon 4 tepki 16.
All these are now added to the package.json
Btn bunlar pakete eklendi. json ve tabii
and of course installed in the node modules folder and once this did finish, we are ready to move on and write
ki node modlleri klasrne yklenir ve bu tamamlandktan sonra, ilk testimize devam etmeye
our first test.
ve yazmaya hazrz.
So here it did finish,
te burada bitirdi,
now let's write our first test and I want to start with writing a test for a component because obviously in
imdi ilk testimizi yazalm ve bir bileen iin bir test yazma ile balamak istiyorum nk ak
react,
bir ekilde
we talk constantly about components
reaksiyonda, biz srekli bileenler hakknda konuuyoruz,
so why don't we start with testing one.
bu yzden neden bir test ile balamyoruz.
Now let me start with a functional component here because that's of course a super easy way of testing
imdi burada ilevsel bir bileenle balayalm. nk elbette ki bu testin ok kolay bir yolu
and then we'll also move to containers and thereafter, to redux.
ve daha sonra konteynrlara geeceiz ve sonra yeniden doacaz.
Now I want to start with my navigation items component here, in the navigation folder in the components
imdi, gezinme eleri bileenini, bileenler klasrndeki gezinme klasrnde, gezinme eleri bileeniyle
folder, that's the navigation items component,
balatmak istiyorum. imdi, reaksiyon bileenlerinin ounun
now keep in mind most of your react components are just functions and therefore they only depend on
yalnzca ilevler olduunu ve bu nedenle yalnzca aldklar sahne paralarna bal olduklarn unutmayn. test
the props they receive,
etmek iin aklnzda
that's something you have to keep in mind for testing.
bulundurmanz gereken bir ey var.
Now let's create a testing file for this component,
imdi bu bileen iin bir test dosyas oluturalm, bundan dolay ayn klasrde
therefore next to it in the same folder, I'll add a new file which I'll name NavigationItems.test.js
yannda, ben NavigationItems adn vereceim yeni bir dosya ekleyeceim. lek.
the .test.js is important because that is automatically picked up by create react
js. lek. js nemlidir, nk zel bir komut altrdktan
app once
sonra tepki
we run a special command and will then be included in the testing and therefore will be tested.
uygulamas oluturularak otomatik olarak alnr ve daha sonra teste dahil edilir ve bu nedenle test edilir.
Now inside this test file, I now can start writing my test and a test uses just by default and just on
imdi bu test dosyasnda, imdi testimi yazmaya balayabilirim ve bir test sadece varsaylan olarak kullanr ve dier
the other hand gives us a couple of methods to define the test.
yandan da testi tanmlamak iin birka yntem sunar.
The first important method is the describe method,
lk nemli yntem tarif yntemidir,
you don't need to import it in that file,
bu dosyaya aktarmanz
it will automatically be made available in our create react app project
gerekmez, test komutunu altrdmzda otomatik olarak
once we run the test command. Describe is a function that takes two arguments, the first is just a description
yaratma tepkisi uygulamas projemizde kullanlabilir. Tanmlamak iki argman alr bir fonksiyon, ilk sadece
of the test bundle
bu dosyaya ait test paketinin bir
this file holds
aklamas burada yani
so here I'll simply name this NavigationItems and I'm writing it like a jsx element but that's not required.
bu NavigationItems adn ve ben bir jsx esi gibi yazacam ama bu gerekli deildir.
This is only what you'll see later in the console output
Bu sadece konsol ktsnda greceiniz eydir, bu yzden
so it should be something which allows you to identify which kind of tests we'll run here.
burada hangi tr testlerin alacan belirlemenize izin veren bir ey olmaldr.
The more interesting part comes in a second argument, that is your testing function.
Daha ilgin olan ksm ikinci bir argmana geliyor, bu sizin test fonksiyonunuz.
It's a normal javascript function and I'll use an ES6 arrow function here, in here you're going to
Bu normal bir javascript ilevi ve burada bir ES6 ok ilevi kullanacam,
describe, you're going to write your actual tests. Now to do that,
burada tanmlayacaksnz, gerek testlerinizi yazacaksnz. imdi bunu yapmak iin,
you write a test by writing it,
yazarak bir test yazyorsunuz, bu
that's another function which will just be available.
sadece mevcut olacak baka bir ilev.
It describes or allows you to write one individual test,
Bireysel bir test yazmanz ya da tanmlamanz salar, ayrca
it also takes two arguments.
iki argman da alr.
The first one is again just a string, a description which will appear in the console
Birincisi yine sadece bir dizgedir, konsolda grnecek bir tanmdr ve tipik
and typically you just complete the sentence so it and then you describe what it should do.
olarak sadece cmleyi tamamlarsnz ve sonra ne yapmas gerektiini tarif edersiniz.
So it should
Bu yzden, imdi ve
and now let's look into our NavigationItems component,
imdi NavigationItems bileenimize bakalm,
let's say by default if we're unauthenticated, this component should render one navigation item,
yani varsaylan olarak, kimlii dorulanmamsa, bu bileen bir ynlendirme esi oluturmal, ikincisi
the second one should not be rendered and that here it should render one more leading to /auth,
oluturulmamal ve burada bir tane daha liderlik etmelidir.
so it should render to navigation items
Bu nedenle, kimlik dorulamas
if we are not authenticated.
yaplmazsa gezinme elerine yer vermelidir.
So that is what we want to test so let's write the sentence,
Yani test etmek istediimiz
it should render to navigation item elements if not authenticated.
ey bu yzden cmleyi yazalm, eer dorulanmamsa navigasyon esi elerine yer vermelidir.
So this is just my description and it doesn't matter what you write here,
Yani bu sadece benim aklamam ve burada ne yazdnzn nemi
this is not parsed or anything like that, it should just be something meaningful you recognize in a
yok, bu ayrtrlmad ya da bunun gibi bir ey, bir konsolda tanmladnz anlaml bir ey olmal,
console because if the test fails, you want to know which test failed.
nk eer test baarsz olursa, hangi testin baarsz olduunu bilmek istersiniz .
So that's the first argument to the it function,
Yani, bu fonksiyonun ilk argman,
the second argument is now again a testing function describing the actual test, here that is just a normal
ikinci argman artk gerek testi aklayan bir test fonksiyonudur, ite bu sadece normal bir javascript
javascript function
ilevidir. Yine
I'm again going to use an arrow function and in here, we write our actual testing logic.
bir ok ilevini kullanacam ve burada, gerek yazmz yazacaz test mant.
Now what we want to do is we want to create an instance of this component as it would be rendered to
imdi yapmak istediimiz ey, bu bileenin bir rneini dom'a, gerek dom tepkimesine dntrlecek
the dom, to the real dom through react and then have a look into the rendered component and see what
ekilde oluturmak ve sonra ilenmi bileene bir gz atmak ve durumun ne
was rendered for the case that the isAuthenticated prop is false.
olduunu grmek iin neler yapldn grmek istiyoruz. Kimlii dorulanm prop yanltr.
Now you might think that for this, we obviously need to render the entire react application because
imdi bunun iin, tm tepki uygulamasn ortaya koymamz gerektiini dnebilirsiniz
navigation items is just one tiny piece in the entire react application, that is where an enzyme comes
nk navigasyon rnleri tm reaktif uygulamasnda sadece bir kk paradr, yani
in, this testing package. Enzyme allows us to just render this navigation items component standalone independent
bir enzim bu test paketinin iinde gelir. Enzim, dier tm tepki uygulamalarndan bamsz olarak bu
of the entire other react application,
navigasyon bileenlerini tek bana oluturmamza
that's the whole idea behind the enzyme package, that we can really write unit tests, isolated tests, tests
izin verir. Bu, enzim paketinin ardndaki tm fikir, gerekten de birim testleri, izole testler
where we don't need to render the complete react app.
yazabileceimiz, testleri tamamlayamadmz testler. uygulamaya tepki ver.
So let's import enzyme then, I need to import something from enzyme, now I'll come back
O zaman enzimi ithal edelim, enzimden bir ey ithal etmeliyim, imdi buna bir ey geleceim
to that something
ama nce
but first I'll also need to configure enzyme and connect it to my react version. For that,
enzimi yaplandrmam ve tepki versiyonuma balaman gerekecek. Bunun iin, badatrcy almam gerekiyor ve bu
I need to import the adapter and it's a default export so you you may name this whatever you want.
varsaylan bir da aktarmadr, bylece istediiniz her eyi bu ekilde adlandrabilirsiniz.
The adapter from enzyme adapter react 16, this package and from the enzyme package, we now only need to
Enzim adaptrnden gelen adaptr 16'ya, bu pakete ve enzim paketine gre, imdi sadece belirli bir eyi ie aktarmaya ihtiyacmz
import something specific,
var, bu adlandrlm
this is a named export
bir da aktarmadr,
so we need curly braces, the configure function. With these two imports added
bu yzden kvrk parantezlere, konfigrasyon fonksiyonuna ihtiyacmz var. Tanmlanan fonksiyonun yukarsna burada eklenmi olan
here above the described function, we can now execute configure and pass a javascript object to configure.
bu iki ithalat ile, imdi yaplandrmak ve yaplandrmak iin bir javascript nesnesi iletebiliriz.
There we should set up an adapter property and assign new adapter as a constructor function,
Burada bir adaptr zellii kurmal ve bir kurucu ilevi olarak yeni bir adaptr atamalyz,
so this adapter is instantiated with new adapter and that's all, with that enzyme is connected.
bu yzden bu adaptr yeni adaptr ile balatlr ve hepsi bu enzim ile balantldr.
Now we want to render a navigation items component and then look into it, for this enzyme gives us a
imdi bir gezinti eleri bileeni oluturmak ve daha sonra iine bakmak istiyoruz, nk bu
specific helper method we can use,
enzim bize kullanabileceimiz zel bir yardmc
we import that too,
metodu veriyor, biz
it's the shallow function. Shallow is the most popular or the best way of rendering react components
de onu ithal ediyoruz, bu s fonksiyon. S, birok durumda reaksiyon bileenlerinin en popler
in many circumstances,
ya da en iyi
enzyme offers two alternatives which I'll also point you to later but shallow is the one you should
ekilde retilmesidir, enzim size daha sonra da iaret edeceim iki alternatif sunar,
use as often as possible because one thing shallow does is it renders the component with all its content
ancak s olarak kullanmanz gereken slk, s bir eydir nk s bir ey yapar tm ierii
but the content isn't deeply rendered.
ile bileen ama ierik derinden oluturulmaz.
So the navigation items component here has navigation item components but these are only rendered as
Dolaysyla, buradaki gezinme eleri bileeni, gezinme esi bileenlerine sahiptir, ancak bunlar yalnzca yer tutucular olarak ilenir,
placeholders,
bunlarn ierii
the content of them isn't rendered and that of course again is important for creating isolated tests
ilenmez ve elbette, tmyle alt bileen bileenleri oluturmayacamz yaltlm testler oluturmak
where we don't then render a whole sub tree of components,
iin nemlidir. Biz sadece bu bileeni oluturmak
we just want to render this component and know what's inside of it without rendering everything which
istiyoruz ve ierdii bileenlerin iine yerletirilmi olan her eyi render
is nested inside its included components.
etmeden iinde ne olduunu biliyoruz.
So shallow is the method to use here
Bu yzden s kullanmann yntemi burada
and now, we want to render that. So I'll create a constant which I'll name wrapper,
ve imdi bunu yapmak istiyoruz. Bu yzden sarmalayc adn vereceim bir
the name is up to you but wrapper is often used,
sabit oluturacam, adnz size kalm, ancak
where I will call a shallow and now I'll pass navigation items as a react element.
sarc genellikle s olarak adlandrlacam ve imdi bir ynlendirme esi olarak gezinme elerini geireceim.
So for that, I first of all need to import this, I need to import navigation items from
Bu nedenle, ncelikle bunu ie aktarmam gerekiyor. Navigasyon elerini, navigasyon
and that is from the navigation items javascript file which is living next to our navigationstest.
testlerimizin yannda bulunan navigasyon eleri javascript dosyasndan almam gerekiyor.
javascript trip.
javascript gezisi.
With that we can render this here as jsx
Bununla jsx olarak burada yapabiliriz ve
and that's important,
bu nemli,
we pass jsx to the shallow method. For this to work,
jsx'i s ynteme geiriyoruz. Bunun ie yaramas iin,
as always we of course need to import react then because no matter if it's a test or not, the jsx
her zaman olduu gibi, elbette bir tepkiyi ithal etmemiz gerekir, nk bir test
code needs to be converted to its react create element alternative.
olup olmadna baklmakszn, jsx kodunun tepki oluturma eleman alternatifine dntrlmesi gerekir.
So now we're shallowly rendering this and we're storing the result in this wrapper constant,
Yani imdi bunu tamamen yapyoruz ve sonucu bu sarmalayc sabitinde saklyoruz, imdi
now we can have a look into the wrapper in this test. And that's the last part of testing, we now
bu testte sargya bir gz atabiliriz. Ve bu testin son ksm,
our expectation, for that we use another method which is made globally available by jest, the expect method.
imdi beklentimiz, nk global olarak aka, bekletme yntemi ile elde edilebilen baka bir yntem kullanyoruz.
Inside expect, we define our, the thing we want to check
eride bekleriz, kontrol etmek istediimiz eyi burada, yani burada
so here I want to check if the wrapper contains a certain element.
sarcnn belirli bir eleman ierip iermediini kontrol etmek istiyorum.
Now on the wrapper, we can again use a utility function provided by enzyme defined method,
imdi sarcda, yine enzim tanml yntemle salanan bir yardmc fonksiyonunu kullanabiliriz, bu bize sarcya
this allows us to look into the wrapper and see if it contains a certain content
bakmamza ve belirli bir ierik ierip iermediine bakmamza ve
and here I want to find a navigation item.
burada bir navigasyon esi bulmak istiyorum.
So we need to import this too, I'll import navigation item from ./navigation item navigation item,
Bu yzden bunu da ie aktarmalyz, navigasyon esini ithal edeceim. / navigasyon esi navigasyon esi, bunun gibi ve bu yzden
just like that and therefore here in the find method, I now want to find navigation item. Important,
burada bulma ynteminde, imdi navigasyon esini bulmak istiyorum. nemli, bu imdi bir jsx
this now is not a jsx element, it's this normal exported function from the navigation item file.
esi deil, navigasyon esi dosyasndan bu normal da aktarlm ilevi.
Now with that
imdi bunu
imported, we expect
ithal ettike, u anda iyi
well we expect nothing right now,
bir ey beklemiyoruz, sadece
we just say what is our thing we want to check,
kontrol etmek istediimiz ey nedir, onu bulup bulmadmz kontrol
we want to check if we find that, but what is our expectation then? You could say the expectation is that
etmek istiyoruz, ama sonra beklentimiz nedir? Beklentinin, onu bulduumuzu syleyebiliriz,
we do find it
fakat testler
but tests are a bit more flexible than this.
bundan biraz daha esnektir.
You could expect that you'll find it only once or twice or that you don't find it, maybe you want to
Bunu sadece bir ya da iki kez bulacanz ya da onu
test for the opposite
bulamayacanz bekleyebilirsiniz, belki de
so here we have to change something to the expect call,
tam tersini test etmek istersiniz, bu yzden
these are utility methods made available by jest. So we can expect to find the navigation item
burada bir eyleri beklemek iin beklemek zorundayz. . Bu yzden, daha nce de sylediimiz gibi navigasyon
as we said earlier, two times if we're not authenticated, so navigation item to half length is what we can
esini beklediimizde, iki kez dorulanmyorsak, bu yzden navigasyon esinin yar uzunluuna, u anda arayabileceimiz
call now
ve birka
and you see there are a couple of helper methods.
yardmc yntemin bulunduunu grdk.
The length we expect to find is two,
Bulmay beklediimiz uzunluk iki, ikiyi bulmak
we want to find two
istiyoruz, bylece bu
so this is automatically added into an array
bir diziye otomatik olarak ekleniyor
and we want to have this to have a length of 2.
ve bunu 2 uzunlua sahip olmak istiyoruz.
Now it will have isAuthenticated set to false because we're not passing this prop, remember? We're
imdi yanl dorulanm olarak ayarlanm olacak nk bu propay gemiyoruz, hatrladn m? Navigasyon elerini s bir ekilde
just shallowly rendering navigation items, we're not sending any props here.
oluturuyoruz, burada hibir sahne gndermiyoruz.
Now if we render it like this, isAuthenticated is not passed and therefore will be treated as false.
imdi bunu byle yaparsak, Kimlii dorulanr ve bu nedenle yanl olarak deerlendirilir.
So with that, this test should actually succeed.
Bylece, bu test aslnda baarl olmal.
Now let's find out how we can test it then.
imdi nasl test edebileceimizi renelim.
For this let's have a look at the package.json
Bunun iin pakete bir bakalm. json dosyas
file and there, if we scroll all the way to the bottom a little, not all the way excuse me a little
ve orada, eer tm yolu aaya doru kaydrrsak, tm bamllklarmn biraz
bit below our dependencies,
altnda mazur grmyorsak,
we see the scripts section.
komut blmlerini gryoruz.
We know the start script,
Balang komutunu
this runs in the browser,
biliyoruz, bu taraycda
we'll see the build script soon,
alyor, yaknda komut dosyasn
now we need the test script. And we can run this with npm run test or just npm test actually, like start
greceiz, imdi test komut dosyasna ihtiyacmz var. Ve bunu npm run testiyle ya da sadece npm testiyle altrabiliriz,
it's a special script where we don't need to run command.
balangta komut altrmaya gerek duymadmz zel bir betik gibi.
This will now execute all the tests and it will automatically scan for all tests files by looking at
Bu, imdi tm testleri yrtecek ve test sonularna bakarak tm test dosyalarn otomatik
the ending, test.js.
olarak tarayacaktr. js.
Now I never save this file, so I should do so now,
imdi bu dosyay asla kaydetmedim, bu yzden imdi yapmalym,
this will then automatically rerun our tests,
bu daha sonra testlerimizi otomatik olarak
it's watching the test files.
yeniden altrr, test dosyalarn izler.
This warning regarding the polyfill can be ignored,
Polyfill ile ilgili bu uyar grmezden
more interesting is if I expand this that we have one passed tests suite, the tests suite is the described function
gelinebilir, daha da ilgin olursam, eer bir geirilmi test paketine sahip olduumuzu geniletirsek, test paketi tarif edilen
and one passed test in general,
ilevdir ve genel olarak bir
that's the it test here, the it function.
test gemitir, ite burada test edilir.
So our test is passed as we have expected
Bu yzden testimiz beklediimiz gibi geti ve
and this is how we write a test for a component.
bu da bir bileen iin bir test yazmamz.
Now let's add some additional tests to this component before we then also dive into testing other things.
imdi, dier eyleri test etmeden nce, bu bileene baz ek testler ekleyelim.